Finding Aid for James V. Campbell papers, 1830-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James V. Campbell papers 1830-1941
Campbell, James V. (James Valentine), 1823-1890.
1 oversize volumes
(in 5 boxes)
4.2 linear feet
85893 Aa 2
University of Michigan professor of law, Detroit, Michigan, attorney, Michigan Supreme Court justice. Family correspondence, journal of trip to Sandusky, Ohio, in 1844, and lecture materials; also papers of Valeria Campbell, corresponding secretary of the Soldiers' Aid Society of Detroit, U. S. Sanitary Commission, concerning the society, the Detroit Soldiers' Home, and other relief agencies; and University student letters, 1872-1876, of Henry M. Campbell.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated between 1940 and 1943 by Mary Campbell Hays (daughter of Edward D. Campbell). Mrs. Hays donated the Valeria Campbell material on behalf of Mary C. D. Anderson (daughter of Samuel T. Douglass). (Both donors under donor no. 1319 ) A small addition was made in 1993 by Catharine L. Campbell (donor 8148 ). Another addition was received from the Macomb County Genealogy Group (donor no. 8785 ) in 2006.
The collection is open to research.
While called the James V. Campbell papers, this collection is actually a collection of papers of Campbell's family, prominent in legal affairs in Detroit, Michigan, during the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Henry Munroe Campbell (1783-1842), and his wife Lois Bushnell Campbell (d. 1876), brought the family to Detroit in 1826. Henry M. Campbell was born in the upper Hudson River Valley of New York, moved to Buffalo and then in 1826 to Detroit. He worked as a merchant, banker, and judge. Henry and Lois had five children, Valeria (1815-1895), Henry Munroe (1821-1835), James Valentine (1823-1890), Lois, and Elizabeth.
Children of Henry M. Campbell:
Valeria Campbell (1815-1895) was a teacher in Detroit and during and after the Civil War served as secretary of the Soldiers' Aid Society of Detroit, later known as the Michigan Soldiers' Aid Society and the Michigan branch of the U.S. Sanitary Commission.
James Valentine Campbell (1823-1890) was born in Buffalo, New York, and came to Detroit with his family in 1826. He was admitted to the bar in 1844 and entered partnership with Samuel T. Douglass. Campbell served as secretary of the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan 1845-1846, justice of the Supreme Court of Michigan 1857-1890, and Marshall Professor of Law at the University of Michigan 1859-1890. In 1849 he married Cornelia Hotchkiss Campbell (1823-1888). Together they had six children, Henry Munroe (1854-1926), James Valentine (1856-1894), Charles Hotchkiss (1858-1927), Douglass Houghton (1859-1953), Edward DeMille (1863-1925), and Cornelia Lois (known as Nellie).
Elizabeth Campbell Douglass in 1856 married Samuel Townsend Douglass (1814-1898), the law partner of James V. Campbell. Douglass moved from Fredonia N.Y. to Detroit in 1837, where his cousin Douglass Houghton was a leading physician and State Geologist, and entered the law office of Henry N. Walker and Asher B. Bates. In 1840 Bates retired and Douglass became Walker's partner. In 1844 James V. Campbell became a member of the firm now called Walker, Douglass and Campbell. Elizabeth (Campbell) Douglass and Samuel T. Douglass had three children: Mary Campbell Douglass, who attended the University of Michigan, 1874-1876, and married Frederic P. Anderson of Grosse Ile, Michigan; Benjamin Douglass (1859-1911), an 1882 engineering graduate of the University of Michigan and engineer for several Detroit companies; and Elizabeth C. (Lily) Douglass.
Children of James V. Campbell:
Henry Munroe Campbell (1854-1926) graduated from the University of Michigan in 1876 and University of Michigan Law School in 1878. He became the law partner of his brother Charles and of Henry Russel. He served as a delegate to Michigan's 1908 Constitutional Convention.
James Valentine Campbell (1856-1894) was a broker in Detroit.
Charles Hotchkiss Campbell(1858-1927) graduated from the University of Michigan in 1880, and became law partner of his brother Henry and of Henry Russel.
Douglass Houghton Campbell (1859-1953) graduated from the University of Michigan in 1882, and received his Ph.D. there in 1886. He later studied in Germany and became professor of botany at Stanford University.
Edward DeMille Campbell (1863-1925) graduated from the University of Michigan in 1886 and became professor of chemistry there. He was blinded in a laboratory accident in 1892.
The James V. Campbell papers include materials documenting Campbell's career as professor of law at the University of Michigan, lawyer, and Michigan stue Supreme court justice as well as papers of other Campbell family members. The papers include family correspondence, a journal of a trip to Sandusky, Ohio, in 1844, and lecture materials; also papers of Valeria Campbell, corresponding secretary of the Soldiers' Aid Society of Detroit, U. S. Sanitary Commission, concerning the society, the Detroit Soldiers' Home, and other relief agencies; and University student letters, 1872-1876, of Henry M. Campbell.
The collection is divided into six series: Family Materials, Charles H. Campbell Materials, Cornelia L. Campbell Materials, Henry M. Campbell (1783-1842) Materials, Henry M. Campbell (1854-1926) Materials, James V. Campbell Materials, Valeria Campbell Materials, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Blind--Michigan.; Campbell, James V. (James Valentine), 1823-1890.; Campbell family.; Charities--Michigan--Detroit.; Christmas.; Detroit Soldiers' Home (Mich.); Anderson, Mary Douglass.; Germany.; Harper Hospital.; Judges--Michigan.; Law.; Michigan Committee for the Relief of the South.; Michigan Soldiers' Aid Society.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Northwestern Sanitary Fair (1863: Chicago, Ill.); Public welfare--United States.; St. Paul's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); Soldiers' Aid Society of Detroit.; Stanford University--Faculty.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States Sanitary Commission.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Law.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; Veterans--Employment--Michigan.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Campbell, Charles Hotchkiss, 1858-1927.; Campbell, Douglas Houghton, 1859-1953.; Campbell, Edward De Mille, 1863-1925.; Campbell, Henry M. (Henry Munroe), 1854-1926.; Campbell, Henry M. (Henry Munroe), 1783-1842.; Campbell, Nellie.; Campbell, Valeria, 1815-1895.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Campbell, James V. (James Valentine), 1823-1890.; Campbell family.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Tintypes.; Photographs.
- Family Materials
  Family Materials is the largest series and consists of visual materials and a chronological sequence of family correspondence, 1834-1941. The photographs include portraits of James V. Campbell, and a lesser number of other family members. The earliest portion of the family correspondence includes letters of the first Henry M. Campbell and several of his children. During the 1850s and 1860s letters of James V. Campbell to his wife and children predominate. These letters concentrate on family matters but also explain to his family Campbell's reactions to his work on the Supreme Court. The bulk of the series consists of letters to Valeria Campbell and Nellie Campbell, most from family members. Many letters from Charles H., Douglass H., and Edward D. Campbell describing their student life at the University of Michigan are found in the 1870s and 1880s. Later letters describe Douglass's studies in Germany, Edward's blindness, and the later lives of all three brothers. Also in the 1870s are found letters to Mary Campbell Douglass while she attended the University of Michigan (no letters from her are included). In the period 1885-1887 a number of letters are found from women active in Soldiers' Aid Societies during the Civil War, collected by Valeria Campbell for a publication of the Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States. This series also includes newspaper clippings and other materials not easily identified with a specific family member.
  - Inventories and notes on the papers 1940s (Box 1)
    (created by staff of Michigan Historical Collections)
  - Visual Materials
    - Photographs
      - James V. Campbell (Box 1)
      - Other family members and friends (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous: drawing of an old house (possibly the house used by the Soldiers' Aid Society, but see the cautionary caption on the picture) and a watercolor (by Edward D. Campbell) of kingbird (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence
    - 1834-1891, 33 folders (Box 1)
    - 1892-1904, 14 folders (Box 2)
    - 1905-1941, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Hotchkiss family miscellanea (Box 2)
- Charles H. Campbell Materials
  - Notebook of legal and random writings 1872-1884 (Box 2)
- Cornelia L. Campbell Materials
  - Notebook (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook relating to the death of James V. Campbell 1890 (Volume 1)
- Henry M. Campbell (1783-1842) Materials
  - Account books, 2 volumes (Box 2)
- Henry M. Campbell (1854-1926) Materials
  Henry M. Campbell (1854-1926) Materials includes letters written while a student at the University of Michigan. Other such letters are found in the main correspondence file in Family Materials.
  - Student letters written while at University of Michigan 1872-1876 (Box 2)
- James V. Campbell Materials
  James V. Campbell Materials includes miscellaneous writings, some of them typescripts of materials held by the Burton Historical Collection, Detroit Public Library. This series also contains manuscripts, poems and stories, written by James V. Campbell. These stories and poems were given as Christmas gifts. The manuscripts are individually bound, and many of them contain clip illustrations glued onto the pages.
  - Address "On the Study of the Law," 1859 (Box 5)
  - Journal of trip to Sandusky, Ohio 1844 (Box 5)
  - Lectures on admiralty and shipping, 2 folders (Box 5)
    [typescripts, originals at Burton Historical Collection]
  - Manuscript ode for dedication of University Hall 1873 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript "Judicial History of Michigan," 1886 (Box 5)
    [typescript, original at Burton Historical Collection]
  - Tablet of legal notes (Box 5)
  - Christmas and other stories
    - Manuscript, untitled Christmas story 1830 (Box 5)
      (includes type transcription)
    - Manuscript "A Trip to Fairy Land", story with illustrations 1838 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Honeylip", story with illustrations 1856 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Legend of King Arthur & Jack's Voyage to the West", poem 1857 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript, untitled Christmas story 1857 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript, untitled story 1860 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Jimmy's Ride", poem 1860 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript, untitled Christmas story 1862 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "How a Little Boy Named Jimmy Helped Santa Claus Out of a Scrape", poem 1863 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Charge of the Mule Brigade", poem 1863 (newspaper clipping inside) (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Merlin Loose", poem with illustrations 1864 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "The Giants", poem with illustrations 1865 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript, untitled Christmas poems 1865, 2 volumes booklets (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Legend of L'anse Creuse", poem with illustrations 1866 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript, untitled Christmas poem 1866 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Good Old Days", poem with illustrations 1867 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "The Strait", poem with illustrations 1868 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "King Rene's Voyage", poem with illustrations 1869 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "The Lost Island", poem with illustrations 1870 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Cruise of the Mercy", poem with illustrations 1871 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Genifrede", poem with illustrations 1872 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Bedabinoqua", poem with illustrations 1873 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Up the Glen", poem with illustrations 1875 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "The Normans", poem with illustrations 1876 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "The Heiress of Lynne", poem with illustrations 1884 (Box 5)
    - Manuscript "Adventures of a Lion", poem with illustrations undated (Box 5)
- Valeria Campbell Materials
  The Valeria Campbell Materials series consists chiefly of correspondence, reports, and other papers created or collected by Campbell in her work as secretary of the Soldiers' Aid Society of Detroit (known after 1863 as the Michigan Soldiers' Aid Society), which served as the Michigan branch of the U.S. Sanitary Commission. (The history of these organizations is complex, and is explained in detail in "History of the Michigan Soldiers' Aid Society, 1861-1865," by Robert Spiro [MHC call number EA/69/S759/H673].) The papers document the societies' efforts to aid soldiers during the war as well as to care for the needs of returning veterans at the war's end. Also included are papers relating to the Detroit Soldiers' Home, Harper Hospital and Soldiers' Home, the Michigan Committee for the Relief of the South, and the Northwest Sanitary Fair. One item unrelated to soldiers' aid is Campbell's Sunday School record book from St. Paul's Church in Detroit.
  - Detroit Soldiers' Home
    - Papers 1863-1867, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Statements and receipts 1865 (Box 3)
  - Harper Hospital and Soldiers' Home record book 1866-1867, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Michigan Committee for Relief of the South papers 1867 (Box 3)
  - Northwest Sanitary Fair papers 1864-1866 (Box 3)
  - St. Paul's Church Sunday School record book 1860-1862, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Soldiers' Aid Society of Detroit and Michigan Soldiers' Aid Society
    - Auxiliaries of the Michigan Branch of U.S. Sanitary Commission, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1861-1870, undated, 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Donations 1861-1866, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Michigan branch societies papers 1862-1886 (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    - Papers 1861-1870, undated, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Papers entitled "Red Cross of the Sixties" and "Miss Valeria and the War" (Box 3)
    - Reports 1862-1865, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Reports, circulars and broadsides (Box 3)
    - Statements and receipts 1863-1868, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Applicants' register of U.S. Sanitary Commission Bureau of Information and Employment 1865 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook relating to Soldiers' Aid Society of Detroit 1863-1864 (Box 4)
Related Material
Papers of James V. Campbell's law partner and brother-in-law Samuel T. Douglass are found in the Douglass family papers, 1812-1911, in the Bentley Library.
Student notebooks of Charles H. Campbell and Edward D. Campbell, and some later work of Edward D. Campbell are found in Charles H. Campbell student notebook, 1879, and Edward D. Campbell papers, 1882-1903, in the Bentley Library.
The Burton Historical Collection, Detroit Public Library, has papers of Henry Munroe Campbell (which also include Michigan Soldiers' Aid Society material), James V. Campbell, Samuel T. Douglass, and the law firm of Douglass and Walker.
Separately cataloged items in the Bentley Historical Library and the University Library include:
Closing remarks of Prof. J.V. Campbell to the graduating class of the Law department, March 21st, 1863. (Bentley call no. DA 2 C188.5 C645)
Closing remarks of Prof. J.V. Campbell to the graduating class of the Law department, March 21st, 1863. (Hatcher call no. HATCH/ARGM: 350 C188cl, electronic version available)
[Pamphlets and articles about Campbell] (Bentley call no. J17 .C1883 A1)
Oration delivered by Hon. James V. Campbell,1861 (BUHR/GRAD: E286 .C19)